{"tossups": [{"question": "This case overturned another whose plaintiff was indicted for robbery in Maryland, called <em>Betts v. Brady.</em> Abe Fortas [FORR-tuss] argued on behalf of this case\u2019s plaintiff before the Supreme Court. An expanded public defender system was set up as a result of this case\u2019s holding. For 10 points, name this landmark case whose plaintiff broke into a pool hall, which held that the Sixth Amendment required the provision of counsel for indigent plaintiffs.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Gideon v. Wainwright</u> </b></em> <u>[</u>Zihan Zhen<u>g]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A member of this profession was assisted by Absalom Jones during a 1793 event in  Philadelphia. The phrase \"your name is mud\" refers to a man with this job. A patriot who died at Bunker Hill, Joseph Warren, had this job. One man with this job encouraged the correspondence of the elderly Adams and Jefferson and was named Benjamin Rush. Members of this profession used a technique popularized by Edward Jenner called inoculation. For 10 points, name this profession whose members once practiced bloodletting and now use tools like the stethoscope.", "answer": "<b><u>doctor</u></b>s [or <b><u>physician</u></b>s; or <b><u>surgeon</u></b>s; or other obvious equivalents] [Jordan Bro<u>wnstei</u>n]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Eug\u00e8ne Albert\u2019s [yoo-zheen ahl-bair\u2019s] system for this instrument has mostly been replaced by one designed by Hyacinth Klos\u00e9 [HYE-uh-synth CLOSE-uh] and named for flute pioneer Theobald Boehm [TAY-oh-bald BAME]. The first of these instruments were produced from a chalumeau [shah-loo-moh] with an added register key. Klezmer [KLEZ-murr] music  prominently features this woodwind instrument, which was was played by such jazz musicians as Artie Shaw and Benny Goodman. For 10 points, name this single-reed woodwind instrument keyed in B-flat, which usually has a black body.", "answer": "soprano <b><u>clarinet</u></b> [accept any other type of <b><u>clarinet</u></b>]  [Rob Carson]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This policy prompted an assassination attempt by Edward Kullman. This policy was accused of being instigated by Freemasons in the <em>Etsi multa</em> [ET-see MOOL-tuh] encyclical of Pope Pius IX [\u201cthe ninth\u201d], and it led to the creation of the Centre party. It was promulgated by the Congregations Law, and the May Laws of Adalbert [AD-uh-burt] Falk tried to institute this policy, which banned the Jesuits. For 10 points, name this attack on the Catholic Church by Otto von Bismarck.", "answer": "<b><u>Kulturkampf</u> </b> [Jason Zhou<u>]</u>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "For 10 points, name this Swiss mathematician who presented a solution to the Seven Bridges of Konigsberg [KOHN-eggs-burg] problem.", "answer": "Leonhard <b><u>Euler</u> </b> [Sriram Pendyala]", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s general Ventidius [ven-TID-ee-uss] drove the Parthians [PAR-thee-uns] out of Asia Minor. His wife Fulvia [FULL-vee-uh] led a faction of senators during a civil war. This man was the target of Cicero\u2019s [SISS-ur-oh\u2019s] Philippic orations. In a Shakespeare play, this man  declares that Brutus \u201cwas the noblest Roman of them all.\u201d This member of the Second  Triumvirate had his forces defeated at the Battle of Actium [ACT-ee-um] during a Civil War against Octavian [ock-TAY-vee-uhn]. For 10 points, name this friend of Julius Caesar and lover of Cleopatra.", "answer": "Mark <b><u>Antony</u></b> [or Marcus <b><u>Antonius</u></b>]  [Evan Adams]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man described Monck Mason\u2019s miraculous three-day trip across the Atlantic in a balloon in a hoax article printed in the <em>New York Sun</em>. In a story by this man, an imprisoned man rubs rancid meat on his tied up hands and is saved from death by rats, and later again by Napoleon\u2019s General Lasalle [luh-sall]. He wrote a story whose narrator murders an old man with a \u201cvulture-like\u201d eye and confesses after hearing a sound from underneath the floorboards. For 10 points, name this author of \u201cThe Pit and the Pendulum\u201d and \u201cThe Telltale Heart.\u201d", "answer": "Edgar Allan <b><u>Poe</u> </b> [Chris Manners]", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "This ruler's successor was given the Shahnama [SHAH-nuh-mah] of Shah Tahmasp [TAH-mosp]. This ruler, who allied with Francis I and sponsored Piri Reis [PEER-ee RAY-iss], was the first ruler served by the Grand Vizier Mehmed Sokullu Pasha [soh-KOOL-uh POSH-uh] and was married to Hurrem Sultan [HOOR-em SOOL-tahn]. This ruler besieged Esztergom [EZZ-turr-gohm] and defeated Louis II at the Battle of Mohacs [MOH-hotch] to conquer Hungary. This ruler, who was nicknamed for his law-giving abilities, seized Baghdad. For 10 points, name this sultan who presided over the peak of the Ottoman Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Suleyman</u></b> the Magnificent [or <b><u>Suleyman I</u></b>; or <b><u>Kanuni</u></b> or The <b><u>Lawgiver</u></b> before mentione<u>d]</u>  [Doug Graebner]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "After declining an invitation from Imelda Marcos, this band was approached by mobs in Manila. Mia Farrow accompanied this band on their trip to India to visit the Maharishi Mahesh Yogi [mah-hah-REESH-ee mah-HESH YOH-gee]. One of this band\u2019s members claimed that they were \u201cmore popular than Jesus.\u201d Sigmund Freud [FROYD] and Bob Dylan are among the many personalities depicted on the cover of this band\u2019s album <em>Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club</em> <em>Band</em>. For 10 points, name this band from Liverpool known as the \u201cFab Four.\u201d", "answer": "The <b><u>Beatles</u> </b> [Kenji Golimlim<u>]</u>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This man is the namesake of the smallest and lightest nuclear weapons unit designed by the United States. After getting his start in the Lawrence County militia, this man was elected to the Tennessee General Assembly and then to the House of Representatives, where he opposed Indian Removal. With James Bowie and William Travis, he died as a volunteer at the Alamo. For 10 points, name this American known as the \u201cKing of the Wild Frontier,\u201d who wore a coonskin cap.", "answer": "Davy <b><u>Crockett</u></b> [or David Stern <b><u>Crockett</u></b>]  [Evan Adams]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This nation\u2019s custom of \u201cmourning wars\u201d may have led to conflicts with the Anishinaabe [ah-nish-uh-NAH-bee], among others, and it signed the Treaty of Fort Stanwix with the British following the Royal Proclamation of 1763. Leaders from this nation such as Joseph Brant allied it with the British during the American Revolution. For 10 points, name this tribal nation, a confederation of six tribes in New York.", "answer": "<b><u>Iroquois</u></b> [EER-uh-koy] Confederacy [or <b><u>Haudenosaunee</u></b>; prompt on \u201cMohawk\u201d]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The sancai [san-tsye] technique of three-color pottery glazing dates to this dynasty. Yang Guifei [yong gwee-fay], one of the Four Beauties, was the consort of this dynasty\u2019s Emperor Xuanzong. It was interrupted by the Second Zhou [zhoe] Dynasty of Empress Wu, and it rose to power after the Sui [sway] dynasty. Its first emperor was Taizong, and Li Po and Dufu were famous poets who lived during this dynasty. For 10 points, name this Chinese dynasty that lasted from 618 to 907.", "answer": "<b><u>Tang</u></b> Dynasty [or <b><u>Tang</u></b> chao]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This play included a scene in which a character is told \u201cThou shalt get kings\u201d to please its author\u2019s patron, James I. The heir Donalbain [DONN-ull-bane] goes into hiding during this play, whose title character is killed after Birnam Wood is brought to Dunsinane [DUNN-sinn-ane]. The three Weird Sisters appear in, for 10 points, what Shakespeare play, which culminates with Macduff slaying the title Scottish king?", "answer": "<em>The Tragedy of</em> <em><b><u>Macbeth</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Drama"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man helped design the M1913 Cavalry Saber which often bears his name. He was a key part of Operation Fortitude, which convinced the Germans he was leading a force to invade Calais [cuh-lay]. This general led an invasion of Casablanca during Operation Torch and helped relieve Bastogne. For 10 points, name this American World War II general who slapped two soldiers.", "answer": "George Smith <b><u>Patton</u></b> Jr.", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "One type of these objects was called a penteconter [PEN-tuh-conn-tur]. A device called the corvus was first used on these objects at the Battle of Mylae [MEE-lay]. These objects were targeted by a claw and a death ray supposedly invented by Archimedes. The trireme [TRY-reem] was a type of this vehicle. For 10 points, name this kind of vehicle, which in the ancient world were often powered by galley slaves with oars.", "answer": "<b><u>ship</u></b>s [or <b><u>galley</u></b>s before mentioned; or obvious equivalents like <b><u>boat</u></b>s]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This musician was accompanied by members of the Paul Butterfield Blues Band during a  controversial performance at the 1965 Newport Folk Festival in which he \u201cwent electric.\u201d <em>Rolling Stone</em> twice claimed that the greatest song of all time was the first single from this man\u2019s album <em>Highway 61 Revisited</em>. For the point, name this Minnesota-born singer-songwriter of  \u201cLike a Rolling Stone\u201d.", "answer": "Bob <b><u>Dylan</u></b> [or Robert Allen <b><u>Zimmerman</u></b>]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This man successfully negotiated his opponents\u2019 evacuation of Chippenham in the</u></b> <b><u>Tr</u><u>eaty of Wedmore [WEDD-more]. This man, who translated the first English versio</u><u>ns of</u></b> <em><b><u>Pastoral Care</u> </b></em><b><u>and</u> </b><em><b><u>The</u> </b></em><b><u>(+)</u></b><em><b><u> Consolation</u></b><b><u>of</u></b><b><u>Philosophy,</u></b></em><b><u> was the subject of a biography by</u> <u>Asser</u><u>[ASS-urr]. This vic</u>tor at Edington established the limits of the (*)</b> Danelaw [DANE-law] by defeating Guthrum [GOOTH-rumm]. For 10 points, name this King of Wessex whose  erudition and successful defense against Vikings made him the first person known as \u201cKing of  England\u201d and only one called \u201cthe Great.\u201d", "answer": "<b><u>Alfred</u></b> the Great [or <b><u>Alfred</u></b> I]  [Matt Wein<u>er]</u>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man\u2019s supporters were described as \u201clooking like the bar scene outta</u> </b><em><b><u>Star Wars</u></b></em><b><u>\u201d in</u></b> <b><u>an</u> <u>election in which he surprisingly won the Washington primary and finished behind Bob</u></b> <b><u>Dole, but ahead of eventual winner (+)</u><u>George H.W. Bush in the Iowa Caucus. The founde</u>r <u>of the charity Operation Blessing Inter</u>national, he is also the founder of the Christian Broadcasting (*)</b> Network. This man commented that Hurricane Katrina was retribution from God while hosting the <em>700 Club</em>. For 10 points, name this Christian televangelist.", "answer": "Pat <b><u>Robertson</u></b> [or Marion Gordon <b><u>Robertson</u></b>]  [Dan Puma]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A depiction of this place in the parekklesion [pare-uh-KLEE-see-onn] of the Chora</u></b> <b><u>[C</u><u>HOH-ruh] Church features Jesus holding the hands of Adam and Eve. This place is</u></b> <b><u>commonly depicted as a \"mouth\" in manuscript paintings, which often feature depicti</u><u>ons</u></b> <b><u>of its</u> <u>[+] \u201charrowing.\u201d The New Testament repeatedly refers to its inhabitants \u201cweeping</u> <u>and g</u>nashing\u201d their (*)</b> teeth.This place is depicted in the right-hand panel of Bosch\u2019s <em>Garden</em> <em>of Earthly Delights</em> and is usually on the right in paintings of the Last Judgement. For 10 points, name this place often described as a location of eternal torment.", "answer": "<b><u>Hell</u> </b> [Douglas<u> Gra</u>ebner]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>Jill Lepore wrote about this man\u2019s sister Jane in</u> </b><em><b><u>Book of Ages</u></b></em><b><u>. He never reconciled with</u></b> <b><u>his</u><u> son William, a Royalist governor of New Jersey. John Sevier was elected to govern a</u></b> <b><u>short-lived (+)</u><u> state in modern-day Tennessee named for this man. This man drafted th</u>e <u>Plan of Union</u> as a delegate to the Albany Conference, and drew the (*)</b> \u201cJoin or Die\u201d political cartoon. This man created America\u2019s first library and invented the bifocals. For 10 points, name this American statesman who legendarily used a kite to experiment with electricity.", "answer": "Benjamin <b><u>Franklin</u></b> [or Ben <b><u>Franklin</u></b>]  [Mike Bentley]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This product was blended with more palatable herbs in order to create</u> </b><em><b><u>madak</u></b></em><b><u> [mah-</u><u>do</u><u>kk]. The two principal areas of modern creation of this product are called the Golden</u></b> <b><u>Crescent and the Golden Triangle. This product names a conflict during which the</u><u> (+)</u> <u>Taku forts were destroyed that was sparked by the boarding of the</u> </b><em><b><u>H. M. S. Arrow</u></b></em><b>. A letter to Queen Victoria asking why this commodity was legal in her country was written by (*) </b>Lin Zexu, who angered British merchants by destroying large amounts of it. For 10 points, identify this narcotic drug whose trade sparked two wars between China and Britain.", "answer": "<b><u>opium</u></b> [or <b><u>heroin</u></b>; or <b><u>yapian</u></b>; accept <b><u>Opium War</u></b>s] [Will Alston<u>]</u>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The \u201cRammer Jammer\u201d cheer is performed by this team\u2019s fans and its Million Dollar</u></b>  <b><u>Band. All-American linebackers from this school include Cornelius Bennett, Derrick</u></b> <b><u>Thomas, and DeMeco Ryans. Despite having star quarterbacks like Ken</u><u> (+) Stabler</u> and <u>Joe Namath</u><u>[NAY-muth], this team lacked a Heisman winner until Mar</u>k Ingram in 2009. This SEC team\u2019s most recent national championship win came in (*)</b> 2012 over Notre  Dame. They play in a stadium named in part for \u201cBear\u201d Bryant and contest the Iron Bowl against  Auburn. For 10 points, name this team, nicknamed the Crimson Tide.", "answer": "<b><u>Alabama</u></b> Crimson Tide [accept <b><u>Crimson Tide</u></b> before mention; prompt on \u201cthe Tide\u201d]  [Dennis Loo]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man had no choice but to prop up his competitor, the Tennessee Coal and Iron</u></b> <b><u>co</u><u>mpany, in order to prevent the failure of the Moore and Schley broker house. This m</u><u>an</u></b> <b><u>lent crucial money to the federal government during both the Panic of (+)</u><u> 1893 and the</u> </b> <b>Panic of 1907. This man amalgamated Thomas Edison\u2019s firm into General Electric in 1892, </b> <b>in practice for his largest combination which involved Andrew (*)</b> Carnegie and other magnates. For 10 points, name this creator of U.S. Steel, a financier who named a long-running twentieth-century bank.", "answer": "J.P. <b><u>Morgan</u></b> [or John Pierpont <b><u>Morgan</u></b>]  [Matt Weiner]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country\u2019s lore includes a \u201cplain of joy\u201d called Mag Mell, and a land of youth called</u></b>  <b><u>Tir na nog. One of this country\u2019s culture heroes defends a brown bull from being stolen by</u></b>  <b><u>single-handedly engaging</u> (+) Queen Medb\u2019s [MAYV\u2019s] warriors during the Cattle Raid of <u>Cooley. Another legendar</u>y hero of this country gained wisdom by tasting the (*)</b> salmon of knowledge. This country\u2019s folk heroes include Cuchulain and Finn McCool. For 10 points, name this country whose mythology is described in the Ulster Cycle, a manuscript of which is in its city of Dublin.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Ireland</u> </b> [Ike Jose]", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}], "bonuses": []}